Alpheus Hyatt II Papers
Alpheus Hyatt II Papers
1854-1958
Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902.
4.0 linear ft.
Correspondence, diary, expedition journal, financial material, scientific notebook and sketches, photographs, published material, including articles and newspaper clippings, and scrapbooks. Correspondence (1854-1902) includes that of Alexander Agassiz, Charles E. Beecher, E.D. Cope, James D. Dana, J.S. Diller, G.K. Gilbert, G. Brown Goode, Asa Gray, Robert T. Hill, Anna Hyatt Huntington, Hyatt’s father, Alpheus Hyatt, Audella Beebe Hyatt, Jules Marcou, Harriet Randolph Hyatt Mayor, A.S. Packard, Charles Schuchert, and Charles Walcott.
149069
Biographical History
Alpheus Hyatt II, naturalist, paleontologist, and educator, was born in Washington, D. C. an April 5, 1838, the son of Alpheus and Harriet Randolph (King) Hyatt. He attended various private schools, including the Maryland Military Academy, and then entered the class of 1856 at Yale. After completing his freshman year, however, he dropped out for a year of travel in Europe with his mother, upon his return he entered Lawrence Scientific School of Harvard University. As an outstanding pupil of Louis Agassiz, he graduated with highest honors in 1862. He then enlisted as a private in the Massachusetts Volunteer Infantry for the Civil War, emerging with the rank of captain.
At the end of his service, Hyatt decided to pursue his scientific studies, working for a time at the Essex Institute at Salem, Mass. where he and other naturalist friends founded and for a number of years edited the "American Naturalist". In 1867 he was appointed one of the curators of the Essex Institute, working with his friends A. S. Packard, A. E. Verrill, E. S. Morse, and Alexander Agassiz. He took an active part in the foundation of the Peabody Academy of Science. In 1867 he married Audella Beebe and soon became the father of Alpheus Hyatt III, Harriet Randolph Hyatt and Anna Vaughn Hyatt. A second son died in infancy. In 1871 Hyatt was elected custodian of the Boston Society of Natural History, becoming its curator in 1881 and remaining the scientific head of the society until his death in 1902. After 1873 he made his home in Cambridge where he could be near the great collection of fossil cephalopods of the Museum of Comparative Zoology which were his first scientific love. In 1879 he established a summer laboratory for the study of marine zoology at his country home at Annisquam, Mass. He kept a 60 foot schooner with which he made scientific cruises along the New England coast to study fossils and the general geology of these regions. But the location was found unfavorable for the site of a general marine laboratory, so after a few years the station was moved to Woods Hole, Mass., and Hyatt became the first president of its board of trustees.
As an educator, Hyatt served as professor of zoology and paleontology at M.I.T., a chair he held for eighteen years. He also was professor of biology and zoology at Boston University from 1877 until his death. His scientific studies revolved around the lower forms of animal life and was one of the first to combine the study of both living and fossil forms. In 1875 he was elected a fellow of the National Academy of Sciences and in 1898 received the honorary degree of L1. D. from Brown University. His studies took him ton y parts of the world. He died at his home at Cambridge in 1902.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alpheus Hyatt II Papers include biographical material, correspondence, manuscripts, published material, and related items.
Correspondence includes letters incoming, outgoing, letters to and from others, and two letterbooks. One letterbook contains letters from his wife, dated 1889. The other contains miscellaneous correspondence. Subject File includes various materials, such as artifacts, bills and vouchers, Civil War materials, a diary entitled "Travel Book," an expedition journal, a map, mortgages and bills of sale, and photographs. Manuscripts includes holograph papers, notes, and artifacts by Professor Hyatt collected in a large folder, a scientific notebook, and a scientific sketches. Published Material includes articles and newspaper clippings about Alpheus Hyatt II and others. Oversize contains two large photographs, one of an unidentified person and the other of Professor Hyatt's desk.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence, subject file, and manuscripts are arranged alphabetically. Outgoing correspondence are arrange chronologically. Published Materials are organized alphabetically by type and then chronologically.
Related Material
The has numerous collections for the Hyatt-Mayor families. For information on members of the Hyatt, Mayor, Beebe, and Huntington families see for the finding aids of individual family members.
Subject and Genre Headings
Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910.; Beecher, Charles Emerson, 1856-1904.; Cope, E. D. (Edward Drinker), 1840-1897.; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895.; Diller, J. S. (Joseph Silas), b. 1850.; Gilbert, Grove Karl, 1843-1918.; Goode, G. Brown (George Brown), 1851-1896.; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888.; Hill, Robert Thomas, 1858-1841.; Hyatt, Alpheus, 1838-1902 -- Archives.; Hyatt, Audella Beebe, 1840-1932.; Marcou, Jules, 1824-1898.; Mayor, Harriet Randolph Hyatt, 1868-1960.; Schuchert, Charles, 1858-1942.; Walcott, Charles D. (Charles Doolittle), 1850-1927.; Huntington, Anna Hyatt, 1876-1973.; Hyatt, Alpheus.; Hyatt family.; Mayor family.; Paleontologists -- United States.; Paleontology.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Drawings (visual works); Notebooks.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Scientists.; Paleontologists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Anna Hyatt Huntington, 1965-1967.
Inventory
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - A (Box 1)
    - Agassiz, Alexander (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - Beecher, Charles E. (Box 1)
    - C (Box 1)
    - Cope, E. D. (Box 1)
    - D (Box 1)
    - Dana, James D. (Box 1)
    - Diller, J. S. (Box 1)
    - E - G (Box 1)
    - Gilbert, G. K. (Box 1)
    - Goode, G. Brown (Box 1)
    - Gray, Asa (Box 1)
    - H (Box 1)
    - Hall, James (Box 1)
    - Hill, Robert T.
      - 1889-1893 (Box 1)
      - 1895 (Box 1)
    - Hyatt, Alpheus I.
      - 1854 (Box 1)
      - Jan.-May 1855 (Box 1)
      - Jun.-Dec. 1855 (Box 1)
      - 1856 (Box 2)
      - 1857 (Box 2)
      - 1858 (Box 2)
      - 1859 (Box 2)
      - 1860 (Box 2)
      - 1861 (Box 2)
      - 1862, 1864 (Box 2)
    - Hyatt, Alpheus III.
      - 1891, 1895-1896 (Box 2)
      - 1897-1900, Undated (Box 2)
    - Hyatt, Audella
      - 1873, 1876 (Box 2)
      - 1877, 1880-1881, 1883 (Box 2)
      - 1885 (Box 2)
      - 1886 (Box 2)
      - 1887 (Box 2)
      - 1888 (Box 2)
    - Hyatt, Audella
      - 1890 (Box 3)
      - 1891 (Box 3)
      - 1896-1897 (Box 3)
    - Hyatt, Harriet R. (mother)
      - 1856, 1861, 1867, 1870, 1871 (Box 3)
      - 1892, 1894, 1895, 1896, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
    - Hyatt, Harriet R. (daughter), See Mayor, Harriet Hyatt
    - Hyatt, Ida (Box 3)
    - I - L (Box 3)
    - Lowell, Augustus (Box 3)
    - M - N (Box 3)
    - Marcou, Jules (Box 3)
    - Mayor, Harriet Hyatt (Box 3)
    - P - R (Box 3)
    - Packard, A. S. (Box 3)
    - Reusch, Hans (Box 3)
    - S (Box 3)
    - T - U (Box 3)
    - W (Box 3)
    - Walcott, Charles (Box 3)
    - Unidentified (Box 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - 1862, 1863, 1883, 1887, 1888, 1890, 1897 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence To and From Others
    - Correspondence Subject:
      - Letterbook:
        - 1889 letters from wife (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Subject File
  - Artifacts (Box 4)
  - Bills and Vouchers (Box 4)
  - Blueprint and Maps (Box 4)
  - Civil War Materials: (Box 4)
    - List of Officers (Box 4)
    - 1862 (Box 4)
    - 1863 (Box 4)
    - 1864 (Box 4)
    - 1865 (Box 4)
  - Diary "Travel Book" (Box 4)
  - Expedition Journal, 1885 (Box 4A)
  - Invitation to Inaugural Ball, 1889 (Box 4A)
  - Legal Papers (Box 4A)
  - Mortgages and Bills of Sale (Box 4A)
  - Photographs (Box 4A)
- Manuscripts
  - Papers and Articles (Box 5)
  - Scientific Notebook (Box 6)
  - Scientific Sketches (Box 6)
- Published Material
  - Newspaper clippings about Alpheus Hyatt II (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings about others, 1858; 1865 (Box 6)
- Oversize
  - 4 scrapbooks (Box 7)
  - Numerous scientific writings, drawings, and photographs (Box 7)